so recently it turned out that there was
a pretty meaningful response to a short
video that someone shot and Tom the
glitch in the matrix and well it's it's
a lot easier to create a video than it
is to try to write things down in a
medium post so I thought I might try
creating a series of short videos and
see if there's any real interest most
likely the viewership of that video was
actually generated by the fact that
Jordan Peterson tweeted it so most
likely nobody will actually watch these
videos but if some people do and if it
has some value than it was worth doing
so here we go as an experiment the first
video I thought I might want to play
with an idea it's actually kind of
difficult to to explain in writing but
it might actually be pretty easy to
explain in in video and I think it's
it's not common currants and I think is
pretty helpful so the idea is to say
that there is say in a social
environment we can we can imagine a
couple of different layers and this is
just a useful way of partitioning
certain kind of social phenomenon so we
might say for example there's a
financial layer that is about the way
that money flows and agreements around
money works there's an economic layer
which is about physical infrastructure
about skills about the distribution and
resources and where people are working
and things like that there is the
socio-political layer which is things
like but the effectiveness the
legitimacy trust in various kinds of
social institutions including schools
and government and things like that and
then there's the the cultural layer
which is kind of the degree to which
people in a given society share values
and most importantly consider each other
to be inside some kind of cultural loop
whereby they don't treat each other as
either arms-length trading partners or
even worse as potential enemies and so
the first idea is that you can think
about a social environment using those
those layers and
the second and in this case the more
important point is to think about the
way that the layers can actually be
traded off against each other so
specifically I quite specifically
imagine what happened in 2008 during the
2008 financial crisis that whether this
is done consciously or unconsciously a
decision was made to prevent or inhibit
the negative consequences at the
financial and to a lesser but very
important extent economic layer by
actually spending resources or burning
resources at the social political and
even at the cultural level right so you
might imagine that roughly around the
time that say for example tarp and the
various bailout decisions were being
made that it could have gone either way
and that we could have for example
allowed the too-big-to-fail entities to
fail and this would have had negative
consequences that sort of the financial
level and negative consequences probably
at the economic level and even negative
consequences at the political level the
people who've had some you know as the
pain of crashing market to that as the
pain of unemployment got passed on to
the people they would have probably been
very unhappy at a political level of me
if voted the rascals out however it
would have kept it in that order right
and so eventually as the negative
consequences the financial crisis played
its way out and say all the bank's
disappeared some kind of new approach
say for example Google innovating an
entirely novel way of handling banking
questions or the emergence of an
entirely different regime would have
come into place and we would have moved
forward
effectively no damage being done at the
cultural level instead a choice was made
to save bail out the the too-big-to-fail
entities protect the integrity of the
financial system and the economic layer
and modeled as we currently have it and
I would propose that this was being this
it was done at the cost of political
particular and also at the cost of
cultural capital so quite specifically
what I would say is that things like the
Trump phenomenon and brexit are directly
and linearly connected to the various
bailouts that happened in the United
States in Europe but it was a Direct
Subsidy the political and cultural layer
subsidized the economic and the
financial layer at cost to the political
and cultural layer and so as an example
of a similar historical circumstance you
can take a look at what happened in the
United States and in Germany in the
context of the Great Depression in the
1930s that in the United States the
financial the depression hits the
financial layer quite badly it burned
down to the economic layer hit the
economic layer quite badly it burned
under the political layer which is to
say that the Republicans were voted out
and the Democrats were voted in and you
had a meaningfully significant change to
the nature of what American politics
looked like vastly more centralization
around the executive but it didn't
meaningfully burn down to the cultural
level and in many ways it actually made
the cultural level stronger well by
contrast in Germany the financial crisis
went to hyper inflation which vaporized
the entire financial system which
hammered the economic system and led to
a terrible terrible economic depression
which in fact went all the way down to
vaporize the political layer and led to
the collapse of the Weimar Republic
which then of course even penetrated
into the cultural layer and led to
things like the Holocaust where Germans
turned against Germans and the notion of
what it even meant to be part of a
culture became problematised
so so this is the framework and the the
proposition is that we're now currently
living out the consequences of that that
decision and that the the progress the
decision - the choice to continue to
subsidize and support the financial
layer and the economic layer at the cost
of the political and the cultural layer
is risky because it the layers work in
that direction we know the cultural
foundation is foundational and while it
may be unhappy to endure a financial
crisis it is kind of strophic to endure
a cultural crisis civil wars happen when
you have political breakdown genocides
have them you have cultural breakdown
and so
it might be useful to think about these
costs explicitly when choices are being
made in response to various challenges
as they come up over the next couple of
years